Neural Networks are a pretty old
ニューラルネットワークは
algorithm that was originally motivated
極めて古いアルゴリズムで、もともとそれは
by the goal of having machines that can mimic the brain.
脳を模倣する機械を得る事を目標としていた。
Now in this class, of course
このクラスではもちろん、
I'm teaching Neural Networks to you
ニューラルネットワークを教えるのは
because they work really well
異なる種類の機械学習の
for different machine learning problems and
問題で、それがとても役立つからで、
not, certainly not because they're logically motivated.
論理的な動機づけによる、という訳では無い。
In this video, I'd like
だがこのビデオでは
to give you some of the background on Neural Networks.
ニューラルネットワークのある程度の背景知識を教えたい、
So that we can get a sense of what we can expect them to do.
それらが何をしてくれるか、の感覚を養うために。
Both in the sense of
こんにち的な機械学習野問題に
applying them to modern day
適用する、という意味でも、
machinery problems, as well as for
あなたがたの中に
those of you that might
将来の大きな
be interested in maybe the
AIの夢を見る人々が
big AI dream of someday
いつの日か真の
building truly intelligent machines.
知的な機械を作る為にも。
Also, how Neural Networks might pertain to that.
ニューラルネットワークがそれにどのように関係するのかも。
The origins of Neural Networks was
ニューラルネットワークの起源は
as algorithms that try
脳を模倣しようとした
to mimic the brain and
アルゴリズムにあり、
those a sense that if we
それは理解も出来る。
want to build learning systems
学習システムを作ろう、と思ったら
while why not mimic perhaps the
何故この、恐らくもっとも驚くべき
most amazing learning machine we
学習する機械である所の、
know about, which is perhaps the
この脳を模倣しないというのか？いや、する（反語）
brain. Neural Networks came to
ニューラルネットワークは
be very widely used throughout the
1980年代から1990年代にかけて、
1980's and 1990's and
とても広く使われていた。
for various reasons as popularity
だが様々な理由で
diminished in the late
90年代の後半には人気は下火となっていた。
90's. But more recently,
だがより最近になって、
Neural Networks  have had a
ニューラルネットワークは
major recent resurgence.
大復活を遂げた。
One of the reasons for this
この復活劇の理由の一つには
resurgence is that Neural Networks
ニューラルネットワークは
are computationally some what
計算量的になかなか
more expensive algorithm and
高く付くアルゴリズムだというのがある。
so, it was only, you know,
だから近年になってようやく
maybe somewhat more recently that
大規模なニューラルネットワークを走らせるのに
computers became fast enough
十分なくらいコンピュータが
to really run large scale
速くなった。
Neural Networks and because of
その為、
that as well as a
その他幾つかの
few other technical reasons which we'll
技術的な理由も手伝って
talk about later, modern Neural
それについては後ほど話すが、
Networks today are the state
モダンなニューラルネットワークはこんにちの
of the art technique for many applications.
ステートオブアートな技術として、様々に応用されている。
So, when you think about mimicking
では脳を模倣しよう、と考えると、
the brain while one of
人間の脳というのは
the human brain does tell me same things, right?
とてもたくさんの素晴らしい事が出来る、でしょ？
The brain can learn to
脳は画像処理を
see process images than to
学習する事も出来るし、
hear, learn to process our sense of touch.
聞き取りも学習出来るし、感触の処理も学習出来る。
We can, you know, learn to
数学を
do math, learn to do
学ぶ事も出来るし、
calculus, and the brain
計算学ぶ事も出来る。
does so many different and amazing things.
脳はそれらたくさんの素晴らしい事が出来る。
It seems like if you want
そんなに素晴らしいのだから、
to mimic the brain it seems
その脳を模倣しようとすれば
like you have to write lots of different
たくさんの異なるソフトウェアを
pieces of software to mimic all
書かなきゃいけなさそうに見える、
of these different fascinating, amazing things
これら脳が教えてくれる、
that the brain tell us, but does
様々な魅力的で驚くべき物達を模倣する為に。
is this fascinating hypothesis that the
だが、以下のような仮説があったら、魅力的じゃないか？
way the brain does all of
脳がこれら様々な物事を
these different things is not
行う方法は、
worth like a thousand different programs,
何千ものプログラムによってでは無く、
but instead, the way the
実際に脳が機能するやり方は
brain does it is worth
たった一つの
just a single learning algorithm.
学習アルゴリズムによって、という。
This is just a hypothesis but
これは単なる仮説だが、
let me share with you
この証拠とも取れる事を
some of the evidence for this.
幾つか共有したい。
This part of the brain, that little
脳のこの部分、
red part of the brain, is
この小さな赤い部分は
your auditory cortex and
聴覚皮質だ。
the way you're understanding my voice
そして今あなたが私の声を理解している方法は
now is your ear is
あなたの耳が
taking the sound signal and routing
音声信号を拾い上げて、
the sound signal to your auditory
その音声信号をあなたの聴覚皮質へと送り、
cortex and that's what's
そしてその聴覚皮質こそが
allowing you to understand my words.
私の言葉を理解してくれる訳だ。
Neuroscientists have done the
神経学者は以下のような
following fascinating experiments where
興味深い実験を行なってきた、それは
you cut the wire from
耳から聴覚皮質への
the ears to the auditory
線をカットして、
cortex and you re-wire,
それをつなぎなおすーー
in this case an animal's brain, so
この場合は動物の脳だが、
that the signal from the eyes
目から視神経へのシグナルを
to the optic nerve eventually gets routed to the auditory cortex.
聴覚皮質に送られるように。
If you do this it turns out,
これをやってみると、
the auditory cortex will learn
聴覚皮質は
to see.
見る事を学習する事が分かった！
And this is in every single sense
これは、見る、という言葉から
of the word see as we know it.
想起される全ての事について言える。
So, if you do this to the animals,
だからこれを動物に行うと、
the animals can perform visual discrimination
その動物は視覚による区分のタスクが行え、
task and as they can
つまりそれらの動物は
look at images and make appropriate
画像を見て、それらの画像に基づいて
decisions based on the
適切な決定を行う事が出来る。
images and they're doing
そしてそれらは、
it with that piece of brain tissue.
ここの脳の組織で行うのだ。
Here's another example.
ここにもう一つ別の例がある。
That red piece of brain tissue is your somatosensory cortex.
脳のこの赤い部分は体性感覚皮質だ。
That's how you process your sense of touch.
そこは触覚、触った感触を処理する所。
If you do a similar re-wiring process
同じような再結合処理を行うと
then the somatosensory cortex will learn to see.
体性感覚皮質は見る事を学習する。
Because of this and other
これやその他の
similar experiments, these are
似たような実験のため、、、
called neuro-rewiring experiments.
これらは神経再接続実験と呼ばれるが、
There's this sense that if
こんな意味で、
the same piece of physical
物理的に同じ脳の組織が
brain tissue can process sight
視覚や音や触覚を
or sound or touch then
処理出来るのなら、
maybe there is one learning
学習アルゴリズムも一つで、
algorithm that can process
視覚や音や触覚を
sight or sound or touch.
処理出来ているのかもしれない。
And instead of needing to
そして何千もの
implement a thousand different programs
異なるプログラムを実装する代わりに
or a thousand different algorithms to
または何千もの異なるアルゴリズムを使う代わりに
do, you know, the thousand wonderful things
脳が行なっているような、
that the brain does, maybe what
何千もの素晴らしい事をするのに必要なのは、
we need to do is figure out
ひょっとしたら脳の学習アルゴリズムが
some approximation or to whatever
行なっている事の、何らかの近似を
the brain's learning algorithm is and
見出して、それを実装する事
implement that and that the
かもしれない。
brain learned by itself how to
そしてその脳が実際に
process these different types of data.
これら様々な種類のデータを処理する方法を学習する方法は、
To a surprisingly large extent,
驚く程大部分は、
it seems as if we can
どうやらどんな種類のセンサーも
plug in almost any sensor
脳のほとんどどこにでも
to almost any part of
つなぐ事が出来るようなのだ。
the brain and so, within the
そしてどうやら、そうすると、
reason, the brain will learn to deal with it.
脳はそれをどう扱うかを学習するらしい。
Here are a few more examples.
ここにさらなる例を幾つか用意した。
On the upper left is
上部左は、舌で物を見る事を
an example of learning to see with your tongue.
学習する例だ。
The way it works is--this is
それがどうなってるかというと、
actually a system called BrainPort undergoing
これはBrainPortという、FDAが行なっているシステムで
FDA trials now to help
盲目の人が
blind people see--but the
見えるようになるのを手伝うという物。
way it works is, you strap
それがどうなってるかというと、
a grayscale camera to your
おでこにグレースケールのカメラを付けて
forehead, facing forward, that takes
前に向けて、
the low resolution grayscale image
それが低解像度のグレースケールの像で
of what's in front of you
あなたの前にある物を映す。
and you then run a wire
そして舌に、
to an array of electrodes
電極の配列を
that you place on your tongue
つなげる。
so that each pixel gets mapped
個々のピクセルが
to a location on your
舌の場所に対応するように
tongue where maybe a
そして例えば
high voltage corresponds to a
高い電圧が暗いピクセルに
dark pixel and a low voltage
対応し、低い電圧が
corresponds to a bright
明るいピクセルに対応する、というように。
pixel and, even as
そして今日はじめたとしても、
it does today, with this sort
この種のシステムで
of system you and I will
あなたや私は、
be able to learn to see, you know,
舌で見るという事を、
in tens of minutes with our tongues.
10分やそこらで学習する事になる。
Here's a second example of human
これは二番目の例で
echo location or human sonar.
エコー位置、または人力ソナーだ。
So there are two ways you can do this.
これを行うには2つ方法がある。
You can either snap your fingers,
指を鳴らすか
or click your tongue.
舌を打つかだ。
I can't do that very well.
私はこれ苦手なんですが。
But there are blind people
だが盲目の人がこんにち
today that are actually being
これを実際に
trained in schools to do this
学校で練習して、
and learn to interpret the pattern
環境から音が跳ね返る
of sounds bouncing off your environment - that's sonar.
パターンの解釈を学習している、それがソナーだ。
So, if after you search
youtubeを検索してみると、
on YouTube, there are
実際の動画があるよ。
actually videos of this amazing kid who
悲運にも目玉にガンを患った為
tragically because of cancer
目玉を失った子供が、
had his eyeballs removed, so this is a kid with no eyeballs.
ーーつまりこの子供は目玉が無いのだーー
But by snapping his fingers, he
だが指を鳴らして、
can walk around and never hit anything.
歩き回って何にもぶつからないで済んでる。
He can ride a skateboard.
スケートボードにも乗れて、
He can shoot a basketball into a
バスケットボールのフープに
hoop and this is a kid with no eyeballs.
シュートも出来る。これが目玉の無い子供なのだ。
Third example is the
三番目の例は
Haptic Belt where if
HapticBeltで、
you have a strap
腰の回りに
around your waist, ring up
ストラップをつけて、
buzzers and always have the northmost one buzzing.
ブサーをたくさんつける、そして一番北のブザーがいつも鳴るようにする。
You can give a human a
すると人間に、
direction sense similar to
鳥などが北がどちらかを感じるような
maybe how birds can, you know, sense where north is.
方向感覚を身につける事が出来る。
And, some of the bizarre example, but
そしてちょっと気味が悪い例としては、
if you plug a third eye
カエルに三番目の目を
into a frog, the frog
つなげると、
will learn to use that eye as well.
カエルはその目をどう使うかを学習する、という物。
So, it's pretty amazing to
以上は、極めて驚くべきほどじゃないか。
what extent is as if
ほとんどどんなセンサーを
you can plug in almost any sensor
脳につなげても、
to the brain and the brain's
脳はそのデータから、
learning algorithm will just figure
そのデータをどう扱うかを
out how to learn from that
勝手に学んでいく様が、
data and deal with that data.
いかに広い範囲で成立しているかという事は。
And there's a sense that
そして脳の学習アルゴリズムが
if we can figure out what
どんな物かを見つけ出し、
the brain's learning algorithm is, and,
それを実装する、またはその近似でもコンピュータで
you know, implement it or implement some approximation
実装出来れば、
to that algorithm on a computer, maybe
それはたぶん、
that would be our best shot
それはAI、人工知能、
at, you know, making real progress
その夢みる所の、真に知能を持った機械を作る
towards the AI, the
という野望への、
artificial intelligence dream of
とても大きな
someday building truly intelligent machines.
一歩となりうる。
Now, of course, I'm not
今回はもちろん、
teaching Neural Networks, you know,
ニューラルネットワークを教えるのは
just because they might give us
この遥か彼方のAIの夢への扉を
a window into this far-off
開くから、という訳では無い。
AI dream, even though I'm
とは言うものの、私は個人的には
personally, that's one of the things
その夢が私の研究人生で
that I personally work on in my research life.
追求している物の一つだが。
But the main reason I'm
だがこのクラスで
teaching Neural Networks in this
私がニューラルネットワークを教える主な理由は
class is because it's actually a
それは実際にとても有効な
very effective state of the
ステートオブジアートな、
art technique for modern day machine learning applications.
こんにちの機械学習への応用となっているからだ。
So, in the next
だから今後の一連の
few videos, we'll start diving into
ビデオで、ニューラルネットワークの
the technical details of Neural
技術的詳細に入っていく。
Networks so that you
あなたがこんにち的な
can apply them to modern-day
機械学習の応用が
machine learning applications and get
出来るようになって、
them to work well on problems.
問題に対してうまく機能させられるようになる為に。
But for me, you know, one
だが私にとっては、
of the reasons the excite me  is
それがとってもエキサイトな理由は、
that maybe they give
たぶんそれらが
us this window into
将来には、
what we might do if
人間のように学習する
we're also thinking of
アルゴリズムとはどんなものか、
what algorithms might someday be
を想像させる扉を
able to learn in a manner similar to humankind.
開いてくれる事なのかもしれないけどね。